<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

    <title>What's New in Tellurium 0.7.0</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            We have closed over 200 issues and have included several interesting new features. There have been a lot of
            fundamental changes in Tellurium 0.7.0 as compared to 0.6.0 such as the group locating algorithm, module
            caching, macro command, jquery based APIs and i18n support.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>New features</title>
        <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Santa Algorithm</emphasis>: The Santa algorithm is the missing
                    half of the Tellurium UI module concept. The algorithm can locate the whole UI module
                    at the runtime DOM. After that, you can just pass in UI element's UID to find it in
                    the cached UI module on Tellurium Engine. That is to say, you don't need Tellurium Core
                    to generate the runtime locators any more.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Macro command</emphasis>: Macro Command is a set of Selenium
                    commands that are bundled together and sent to Selenium Core in one call. This will
                    reduce the round trip latency from Tellurium Core to Engine and thus, improve the
                    speed performance. Another advantage for Macro Command is that Tellurium Engine can
                    reuse the locator because many times the commands in the same bundle act on the same
                    UI element or same sub-tree in the DOM.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">UI Module Caching</emphasis>: From Tellurium 0.6.0, Tellurium
                    provides the cache capability for CSS selectors so that Tellurium can reuse them without
                    doing re-locating. In 0.7.0, Tellurium moves a step further to cache the whole UI module
                    on the Engine side. Each UI module cache holds a snapshot of the DOM references for the
                    UI elements in the UI module.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Tellurium New APIs</emphasis>: Tellurium Engine in 0.7.0
                    re-implemented a set of Selenium APIs by exploiting jQuery, plus many more new APIs.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Trace</emphasis>: Tellurium 0.7.0 provides built-in support for the
                    command execution time including execution time for each command, total run time,
                    and aggregated times for each command.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">UI Module Live Show</emphasis>: The show command is used to show
                    the UI module that you defined on the actual web page. The UI module on the web page is
                    outlined and if a user hives over the UI module, the UIDs of the selected UI element's
                    and its ancestors' are shown as a tooltip. 
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">i18n Support</emphasis>: Tellurium now provides support for
                    internationalization of strings and exception messages. Internationalized strings for each
                    locale is provided through a MessageBundle for a specific locale which is of the
                    format
                    <programlisting language="java"><?db-font-size 75% ?>
<![CDATA[
<MessageBundleName>_<language-code>_<country code>.properties.
]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tellurium Maven Archetypes</title>
        <para>
        Tellurium includes two maven archetypes, i.e., tellurium-junit-archetype and
        tellurium-testng-archetype for Tellurium JUnit test project and Tellurium TestNG test project,
        respectively.
        </para>
        <para>
            To create a JUnit Tellurium test project, run
            <programlisting language="java"><?db-font-size 75% ?>
<![CDATA[
mvn archetype:create -DgroupId=your_group_id -DartifactId=your_artifact_id
-DarchetypeArtifactId=tellurium-junit-archetype -DarchetypeGroupId=org.telluriumsource
-DarchetypeVersion=0.7.0
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            To create a TestNG Tellurium test  project, run
           <programlisting language="java"><?db-font-size 75% ?>
<![CDATA[
mvn archetype:create -DgroupId=your_group_id -DartifactId=your_artifact_id
-DarchetypeArtifactId=tellurium-testng-archetype -DarchetypeGroupId=org.telluriumsource
-DarchetypeVersion=0.7.0
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>How to Obtain Tellurium 0.7.0</title>
        <para>
            Tellurium 0.7.0 bundle can be downloaded from
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <quote><link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/aost/downloads/list">Tellurium download site</link></quote>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            You can also find Tellurium core and custom selenium server from the following Maven repositories, respectively.

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <quote><link xlink:href="http://maven.kungfuters.org/content/repositories/releases/org/telluriumsource/tellurium-core/0.7.0/">Tellurium Core</link></quote>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <quote><link xlink:href="http://maven.kungfuters.org/content/repositories/thirdparty/org/seleniumhq/selenium/server/selenium-server/1.0.1-te3/">Custom Selenium Server</link></quote>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
